Finding Aid for the Verne Austin Papers, 1943-1945 LSC.2010.04
UCLA Library Special Collections
Verne Austin papers
1943-1945
UCLA Library Special Collections
Austin, Verne
LSC.2010.04
1.5 Linear Feet (3 boxes and 1 oversize box)
Austin was born in 1894. He was Commander of the 752nd Military Police Battalion of Tule Lake, California from 1943-45. He retired from the U.S. Army as a Lieutenant Colonel. Collection contains records of events and exhibits related to the internment of Japanese Americans at Camp Tule Lake, California between October 1943 and October 1945. Includes copies of official files, biographical materials related to Col. Verne Austin and personal correspondence. Also contains scattered issues of the following newspapers published in the Tule Lake relocation Center: The Tulean Dispatch, Newell Star, and Tsurureiki Shimp. Materials in this collection are primarily in English, with some in Japanese.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942303413606533
Biography
Austin was born in 1894; he was Commander of the 752nd Military Police Battalion, Tule Lake, California, 1943-45; he retired from the United States Army as a Lieutenant Colonel.
Scope and Content
Collection contains records of events and exhibits related to the internment of Japanese Americans at Camp Tule Lake, California, between October 1943 and October 1945. Includes copies of official files of the headquarters of the 752nd Military Police Battalion. Also includes biographical materials related to Colonel Verne Austin and personal correspondence. Also contains scattered issues of the following newspapers published in the Tule Lake Relocation Center: The Tulean Dispatch, Newell Star, and Tsurureiki Shimp. The oversize box contains 2 scrapbooks.
Materials in this collection are primarily in English, with some in Japanese.
Related Material
Japanese American Research Project Collection of Material about Japanese in the United States (Collection 2010). Available at the UCLa Library Special Collections.
Tule Lake Relocation Center (Calif.).; Japanese Americans -- Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945; United States Armed Forces -- Officers -- Archives.; Japanese American Research Project (University of California, Los Angeles); Austin, Verne--Archives.
- The Japanese Situation at Tule Lake, 1.0 linear ft.
  Scope and Contents note
  Records of Events and Exhibits pertaining to the Japanese Situation, Camp Tule Lake, California: October 1943- October 1945. Copies of the official files, Headquarters, 752nd Military Police Battalion, on the Tule Lake incident.
  Also includes miscellaneous biographical materials of Colonel Austin. Box 44 is a continuation of Box 43.
  Also includes correspondence and documents relating to those internees confined in the Army stockade.
  - Correspondence re the donation of the Austin Papers to the Japanese American Research Project, University of California, Los Angeles., February-March 1967; (4 items) (Box 43, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous papers on Austin's military career during World War II., 1943-1946; (9 items) (Box 43, Folder 2)
  - Official chronologies of major events entitled Records of Events., November 3, 1943-October 10, 1945; (24 items) (Box 43, Folder 3)
  - Documentary exhibits (Box 43, Box 44)
    - Minutes of the meeting held at Mr. Best's (Project Director, Tule Lake Camp) office at 8:45 A.M., October 26, 1943; (23pp.) (Box 43, Folder 4)
    - Notes on Japanese demonstration at Camp Tule Lake; prepared by Mount T. Archer, Captain CMP, S-2., November 1, 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 4)
    - Minutes of the meeting held at Mr. Best's office at 1:30 P.M., November 1, 1943; (27 pp.) (Box 43, Folder 4)
    - Minutes of the meeting between the Spanish Consul, Mr. F. de Amat and representatives of internees, 1:10 P.M., at Dining Hall no. 6., November 3, 1943; (27 pp.) (Box 43, Folder 4)
    - Record of Events., November 1943; (10 pp.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - Minutes of the meeting held at Mr. Best's office., November 5, 1943; (12 pp.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - Letter, R.R. Best to Verne Austin., November 5, 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
      re Control of the camp by 752nd MP Battalion.
    - Proclamation [no. 1] by Lt. Col. Austin., November 6, 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
      re the Army's control of the Tule Lake Segregee Center.
    - Memo., n.d. [ca. November 7, 1943]; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
      re Internees' committees.
    - Minutes of the conference with evacuee mess hall supervisors., November 8, 1943; (10 pp.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - Minutes of the meeting between representatives of the evacuees and Colonel Austin and Mr. Best., November 9, 1943; (9 pp.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - Interview minutes with the Spanish Consul, F. de Amat., November 9, 1943; (2 pp.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - A narrative report of activities at Camp Tule Lake., November 1-9, 1943; (11 pp.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - Final train list. Rosters of evacuees transferred from other internment camps., November 10, 1943; (7 pp.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - Minutes of the conference with the evacuee committee., November 10, 1943; (11 pp.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - Minutes of the conference with the evacuee committee., November 11, 1943; (13 pp.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - Agreement entered between the Army of the United States, 752nd Military Police Battalion, and the War Relocation Authority (WRA), Newell, California., November 11, 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
      re the security of the camp.
    - Memorandum, from R.R. Best to Verne Austin., November 11, 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
      re Employment procedure.
    - The Tulean Dispatch, vol. 7, no. 27., November 11, 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
      A mimeographed newspaper published by the internees.
    - Tsurureiko Jiho, no. 109., November 11, 1943; (2 pp.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
      The Japanese section of The Tulean Dispatch.
    - Minutes of the conference with the evacuee committee., November 12, 1943; (12 pp.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - Proclamation no. 2, by Verne Austin., November 13, 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
      re the enforcement of restrictive measures.
    - Typewritten copies of Austin's speech given to the internees., November 13, 1943; (3 pp.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - Memorandum, from R.B. Cozzens, WRA Assistant Director, to Verne Austin., November 13, 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
      re Representatives of internees.
    - The Tulean Dispatch, vol. 7, no. 28., November 13, 1943; ( 2 pp.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - Tsurureiko Jiho, no. 110., November 13, 1943; (3 pp.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - Typewritten copies of the speech given by R.B. Cozzens., November 13, 1943; (5 pp.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - A listing of the names of FBI agents present at Tule Lake Camp to investigate the incident (14 names)., November 12-December 18, 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - A proposed wire dispatch to Spanish Ambassador in Washington D.C., (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
      re the dispatch of a representative of the Spanish Embassy.
    - Memo from Verne Austin to George Yamatani., November 15, 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
      re Visit of a Spanish Consul.
    - Notes written by Lt. Forbes., November 16, 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
      re Meeting between Lt. Col. Meek and block managers during the absence of Verne Austin.
    - Letter of transmittal, Muller to Austin (no report)., November 15, 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
    - Telegram, Spanish Embassy to George Yamatani., November 17, 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 5)
      re Visit of the Spanish Consul of San Francisco.
    - Minutes of the meeting between Army officers and Ward representatives and Temporary Communications Committee of the internees., November 18, 1943; (15 pp.) (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - Telegram, Spanish Consul of San Francisco to George Yamatani., November 18, 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 6)
      re Proposed meeting.
    - Telegram, George Yamatani to Spanish Consul of San Francisco., November 19, 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 6)
      re Reply.
    - Proclamation no. 3., November 19, 1943; (2 pp.) (Box 43, Folder 6)
      re Issuance of an identification badge.
    - A report submitted by Alex E. Sloan, foreman mechanic of the garage., November 19, 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 6)
      re Reluctance of internees to report to work. re Reluctance of internees to report to work.
    - A confidential report submitted by Captain Ben M. Hartman, Liaison Officer., November 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 6)
      re Observations made between November 9 & November 19, 1943.
    - Mimeographed instructions issued for the execution of the Army's search in segregee area., November 22, 1943 (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - Plan for search in segregee area, with appended Instructions for searching groups, Instructions for fire break group, Instructions for operation MP patrols, Instructions for patrol units and Instructions to sound stuck operations., (11 pp.) (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - List of officers in charge of groups in the search operations., (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - List of contraband articles., (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - Pick-up list of [100 troublemakers]., (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - Mimeographed report forms for the search operations., (2 items) (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - Four maps of the Tule Lake Camp for the search parties., (4 items) (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - Memorandum, Austin to Best., November 24, 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 6)
      re Additional stockade fence.
    - Telegram, Spanish Ambassador to George Yamatani., November 24, 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 6)
      re Refusal on the dispatch of the Spanish Consul of San Francisco to the camp.
    - Memorandum, Best to Austin., November 26, 1943; (3 pp.) (Box 43, Folder 6)
      re Hospital and medical service.
    - Notice to Block Managers, issued by Austin., November 26, 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 6)
      re Search for contraband articles and troublemakers.
    - Memorandum, Austin to Best., November 19, 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 6)
      re Request for a brief report on the present status of all center activities.
    - Memorandum, Best to Austin., November 26, 1943; (6pp.) (Box 43, Folder 6)
      re Report on center activities.
    - Warrant of Arrest for Tom Kobayashi and Satoshi Yoshiyama, issued by the Justice's Court, Tule Lake Township, Modoc County, California., November 26, 1943 (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - An itemized list of contraband articles seized by the search groups., November 27, 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - Memorandum, Best to Austin., November 27, 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 6)
      re Prosecution of Tom Yoshio Kobayashi and Satoshi Yoshama [Yoshiyama].
    - Official reports submitted by officers in charge of the groups in the search operations on November 26, 1943., November 26-December 1, 1943; (41 reports) (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - Resolutions pertaining to the complete and satisfactory solution of the incident beginning November 4, 1943 when the U.S. Army took possession of the Tule Lake Camp, Newell, California, resolutions passed by a group of internees., November 29, 1943; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 6)
    - Record of Events., December 1943; (8 pp.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - Notice to Block Managers, issued by Austin., December 2, 1943; (1p.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
      re Relaxation in curfew regulations.
    - Memorandum, Best to Austin., December 2, 1943; (1p.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
      re Report from J.J. Thomas, Supervisor of Evacuee Housing.
    - Itemize lists of contraband articles., (2pp.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - Memorandum, Austin to Best., December 3, 1943; (1p.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
      re Center activities.
    - Notice to all residents of Tule Lake Center, issued by Austin., December 4, 1943; (1p.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
      re Members of the negotiating committee now in military custody.
    - Excerpt of a letter, George Yamatani to Austin., December 4, 1943; (2pp.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
      re activities of block representatives in circulating false rumors.
    - A brief note written by George Yamatani to Austin., December 6, 1943; (1p.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
      re Block representatives who work against the block managers.
    - Minutes of the regular meeting of the Board of Directors of Tule Lake Cooperative Enterprises, Inc., December 6, 1943; (Mimeographed, 3pp.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - Notice to the internees, by Austin., December 8, 1943; (1p.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
      re Essential work done by center residents.
    - An appeal to all co-op members issued by the Board of Directors of Tule Lake Cooperative Enterprises, Inc., December 9, 1943; (7pp.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - Minutes of the special meeting of the Daihysha Kai [characters], representatives of the Board of Directors and the Management Committee of the Tule Lake Cooperative Enterprises, Inc., December 10, 1943; (Mimeographed, 3pp.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - Telegram, Spanish Consul of San Francisco to Isamu Uchida, Negotiating Committee., December 10, 1943; (1p.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
      re Visit and arrival time.
    - Memorandum, Lt. Col. A.H. Moffitt, Jr., EO, Army Service Forces, to Austin., December 11, 1943; (1p.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
      re Visit of Spanish Consul.
    - Official transcripts of the interrogations on Toshio George Kuratomi, Shizuo Kai, Ichiro Hayashi, Mitsuho Kimura, and Isamu Sugimoto., December 11, 1943; (27pp.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - Portions of the minutes of the executive committee meeting, first session, [The Commanders Advisory Council, American Legion, Department of California]., (pp. 6-11. (Box 43, Folder 7)
      The part titled Report of the Special Committee to Investigate the Tule Lake Japanese Relocation Uprising. December 11, 1943.
    - Official report of the Spanish Consul on the meeting with representatives of the internees at Tule Lake., December 13, 1943; (4pp.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - WRA Notice to Block Managers., December 14, 1943; (1p.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
      re Gifts to the people in Army stockade.
    - Minutes of the conference between Army officers and ward representatives., December 12, 1943; (3pp.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - Memorandum, Austin to Commanding General, Ninth Service Command., December 16, 1943; (2pp.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
      re Censorship of mail.
    - A confiscated list of block representatives, obtained at a raid on the headquarters of the block representatives at 1107-C., December 18, 1843; (3pp.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
      The Japanese original and English translation.
    - A report submitted by Willard E. Schmidt, WRA Internal Security Officer., December 20, 1943; (2pp.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
      re Troublemakers.
    - Memorandum, R.M. Pedicord, Principal Medical Officer, to Lieutenant H.F. Harmen., December 22, 1943; (2pp.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
      re Visiting in the hospitals.
      Includes a notice issued by Lt. Harmen, December 22, 1943, re Visiting in the Base Hospital and Closing of Schools.
    - Official transcripts on the interrogation of Asaichi Imai, with 4 photographic exhibits., [December 26, 1943]; (7pp.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
      re the Mess Hall #43 affair.
    - Correspondence re the visit of Dr. Frank H. Smith, Methodist minister, to the Tule Lake Camp., December 22-30, 1943; (3 items) (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - Proposals presented by the Civic Organization Group of the internees in its meeting with Austin., December 27, 1943; (1p.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - Copy of the official memorandum, prepared by Nathaniel P. Davis, Inspector dispatched by the State Department., December 17, 1943; (10pp.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
      re Comparison between Tule Lake and Santo Tomas.
    - Memorandum, Jiro Goto, Assistant Treasurer of the Tule Lake Cooperative Enterprises, to Austin., December 29, 1943; (1p.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - A report submitted by Sergeant Sam Yeramian., December 30, 1943; (1p.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
      re Hospital investigation.
    - A report submitted by Sergeant Yeramian., December 31, 1943; (4pp.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
      re Stockade prisoners rebellion.
    - Distribution by Army Service Forces of Statistical Tabulation concerning Segregated Japanese Population at Tule Lake Segregation Center, a mimeographed one-page statistical report., December 31, 1943; (2 items) (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - Petition submitted to Henry L. Stimson, Secretary of War, by Tule Lake residents., December 7, 1943; (2 items) (Box 43, Folder 7)
      re Recognition of block representatives by the Army. A copy of the petition was forwarded to Austin by Army Service Forces on December 31, 1943.
    - A copy of the signed statement made by the internees in the Army stockade who had solemnly vowed to undergo hunger strike until such time as everyone in the stockade [would] be released back to the colony simultaneously and unconditionally., December 31, 1943; (5 pp.) (Box 43, Folder 7)
    - Record of Events., January 1944; (9pp.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
    - A notice issued by Lieutenant L.G. Schaner, Provost Marshal., January 3, 1944; (1p.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      re Food.
    - Memorandum, Captain T.F. Edwards, Medical Officer, to Austin., January 3, 1944; (1p.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      re Medical examination of the Japanese confined in the stockade.
    - A signed statement made by Harry Nogawa to Sergeant Sam Yeramian, investigator., January 3, 1944; (6pp.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
    - Letter, Austin to Ernest Kozuma, member in the negotiating committee., January 4, 1944; (1p.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      re A meeting of internees to be held January 5, 1944.
    - A notice to block managers issued by Kozuma and Kataoka., January 3, 1944; (2 items) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      re A meeting of new block representatives necessitated by the confinement of almost all of the formerly elected representatives and the Negotiation Committee members in the Army stockade, scheduled at 9:00 A.M., January 5, 1944. The original mimeographed notice.
    - Memorandum, T.F. Edwards, Medical Officer, to Austin., January 4, 1944; (1 p.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      re Hunger strike of the Japanese in the stockade and their conditions.
    - A signed statement made by Hiroyoshi Tsuda to Sergeant Sam Yeramian, investigator., January 5, 1944; (5pp.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      re Hunger strike.
    - Minutes of the block representatives meeting., January 5, 1944; (2pp.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
    - Voice of people. English translation of a notice circulated secretly in the camp., January 5, 1944; (1p.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      re Organized efforts by Tule Lake internees to support the hunger strike staged by those in the Army stockade.
    - Memoranda, Intelligence and Prison Officers to Austin., January 3-4, 1944; (4 items) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      re Lack of security measures and inefficiency at WRA hospital.
    - Memoranda, T.F. Edwards, Medical Officer, to Austin., January 6, 1944; (3 items) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      re Conditions of those on hunger strike.
    - Memorandum, Civic Organization Group to Block Managers., January 7, 1944; (1p.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      re Special meeting of various division and section evacuee workers.
    - A notice to internees by Austin., January 7, 1944; (1p.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      re the end of the hunger strike in the Army stockade.
    - A resolution adopted and passed at the meeting of evacuee division and section heads., January 7, 1944; (2pp.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      re Liquidation of the status quo as maintained by the Daihysha [Block Representatives].
    - Minutes of the special meeting of the divisional heads of the Tule Lake WRA Project., January 7, 1944; (Mimeographed, 4pp.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
    - Minutes of the special meeting of the divisional heads., January 9, 1944; (Mimeographed, 6pp.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      Also includes a report on the tabulation of vote by work crews on the question of whether to return to work or not.
    - A notice to Block Managers by Austin., January 10, 1944; (2pp.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      re Procedure to be followed by the internees in conducting the block meeting scheduled on January 11, 1944.
    - A statement prepared by the divisional heads to be read at the block meeting., January 11, 1944; (2 items) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      re the status quo.
    - What is this so-called 'status quo' (Genjo iji to wa nani ka [characters]); Facts about the Dai-Hyo-Sha (Daihyshakai no zenb[characters])., January 11, 1944; (2 items) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      Also: Equitable distribution of future employment and return to normal condition will aid in the release of the detained persons (Shrai shro kikai kinto [oyobi] griteki na und e no daiippo [characters]). A mimeographed information pamphlet, in Japanese and English, prepared by the group which advocates the liquidation of the status quo, to be distributed at the scheduled block meeting.
    - Minutes of the general meeting of all block managers., January 11, 1944; (2pp.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
    - Reports on the tabulated results of voting on the status quo question at the general meeting on., January 11, 1944; (8pp. and 2 charts. (Box 43, Folder 8)
    - Memorandum, Battalion Intelligence Officer and Senior Internal Security Officer to Austin and Best., January 13, 1944; (1p.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      re Temporary work passes.
    - Report of the informal interview of the responsible men of various divisions with the detained stockade internees, prepared by M. Iwohara, Secretary Pro Tem., January 13, 1944; (Mimeographed, 4pp.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
    - Minutes of the special meeting of the divisional heads of the Tule Lake Center., January 13, 1944; (Mimeographed, 3pp.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
    - Report of the informal interview of the divisional responsible men and the detained stockade internees., January 14, 1944; (Mimeographed, 6pp.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
    - Letter, Consul F. de Amat to Austin, requesting the release of six Issei committee members from the confinement in the stockade., January 14, 1944; (4 items) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      Also: a list of those six Issei, a handwritten draft of Austin's reply, and a transcript of the telephone conversation between de Amat and Austin, January 18, 1944.
    - A petition to Austin, submitted by seven coordinating committee members selected at the meeting of divisional heads., January 13, 1944; (1p.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      re Official recognition by Austin of the coordinating committee members as official representatives of the internees at Tule Lake.
    - An original copy of a notice in Japanese posted by Nihon Aikoku Domei [characters] [Nippon Patriotic League] in various latrines in the camp., January 15, 1944 (Box 43, Folder 8)
      Found on January 15, 1944. Includes an English translation.
    - Memorandum, Colonel J.H. Wilson, Chief of Staff, Ninth Service Command, to Austin., January 15, 1944; (1p.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      re Immediate transfer of resposibility for the internal administration of the Tule Lake Center to the War Relocation Authority.
    - Memoranda exchanged between Austin and Best., January 15, 1944; (2 items) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      re Returning control of the Tule Lake Center to the War Relocation Authority.
    - A notice to the internees, issued by Austin and Best., January 15, 1944; (1p.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      re Recognition of the Coordinating Committee and its seven members as official representatives of the internees.
    - Two anonymous letters received from the stockade., January 15-16, 1944; (Photographic copies, 2 items) (Box 43, Folder 8)
    - Memorandum, Colonel J.H. Wilson to Austin., January 14, 1944; (1p.) (Box 43, Folder 8)
      re A message received from the Office of the Assistant Secretary of War on the release of the segregees in the Army stockade.